<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng"
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng" 
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>


<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->

<!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->

<!--<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng"
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng" 
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#jmh">Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</persName>
               <persName ref="#sbb">Sylvan Baker</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title level="m" ref="#OV">Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace ref="#London_city">London</pubPlace><publisher ref="#Whittaker_Geo">Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="sketch">
            <pb n="177"/>
            <head><title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">AN OLD BACHELOR</title>.
            </head>
            <p>There is no effect of the subtle operation of the association of ideas more universal
               and more curious than the manner in which the most trivial circumstances recall
               particular persons to our memory. Sometimes these glances of recollection are purely
               pleasurable. Thus <persName ref="#OVNarrator">I</persName> have a double liking for <date when="--05-01">May-day</date>, as being the birth-day of a
               dear friend whose fair idea bursts upon me with the first sunbeam of that glad
               morning; and I can never hear certain airs of <persName ref="#Mozart">Mozart</persName> and <persName ref="#Handel">Handel</persName> without seeming to
               catch an echo of that sweetest voice in which I first learnt to love them. Pretty
               often, however, the point of association is less elegant, and occasionally it is
               tolerably ludicrous. <orgName ref="#OVNarratorsFamily">We</orgName> happened to-day to have for dinner a couple of wild-ducks,
               the first of the season; and as the <rs type="person" ref="#OVNarratorsFather">master of the house</rs>, who is so little of an
               epicure that I am sure he would never while he lived, out of its feathers, know a
               wild-duck from a tame,—whilst he, with a little affectation of science, was squeezing
               the lemon and mixing Cayenne pepper with the gravy, two<pb n="178"/> of us exclaimed
               in a breath, <said who="#OVNarrator OVNarratorsMother" direct="true" aloud="true">“Poor <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>”</said>—<said who="#OVNarratorsFather" direct="true" aloud="true">“Aye,”</said> rejoined the <rs type="person" ref="#OVNarratorsFather">squeezer of lemons</rs>, <said who="#OVNarratorsFather">“poor <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Sidney</persName>!
                  I think he would have allowed that these ducks were done even to half a turn.”</said> And
               then he told the story more elaborately to a <rs type="person" ref="#OldBach_young_visitor_OV">young visitor</rs>, to whom <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> was
               unknown;—how, after eating the best parts of a couple of wild-ducks, which all the
               company pronounced to be the finest and the best dressed wild-ducks ever brought to
               table, that <rs type="person" ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">judicious critic in the gastronomic art</rs> limited the too-sweeping praise
               by gravely asserting, that the birds were certainly excellent, and that the cookery
               would have been excellent also, had they not been roasted half a turn too much. <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> has been dead these fifteen years; but no wild-ducks have ever appeared on our
               homely board without recalling that observation. It is his memorable saying; his one
               good thing.</p>
            <p><persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> was, as might be conjectured, an epicure; he was also an old bachelor, a
               clergyman, and senior fellow of <placeName ref="#OldBach_college_OV">* * College</placeName><!--scw: NEED TO FIG OUT HOW TO CODE ELLIPSES-->, a post which he had long filled, being,
               although only a second son, so well provided for that he could afford to reject
               living after living in expectation of one favourite rectory, to which he had taken an
               early fancy from the pleasantness of the situation and the imputed salubrity of the
               air. Of the latter quality, indeed, he used to give an instance, which, however
               satisfactory as confirming his pre-<pb n="179"/>possession, could hardly have been
               quite agreeable, as preventing him from gratifying it;—namely, the extra-ordinary
               and provoking longevity of <rs type="person" ref="#OldBach_incumbent_OV">the incumbent</rs>, who at upwards of ninety gave no sign of
               decay, and bade fair to emulate the age of <persName ref="#Old_Parr">Old Parr</persName>.</p>
            <p>Whilst waiting for the expected living, <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>, who disliked a college residence,
               built himself a very pretty house in <rs type="place" ref="#Shinfield">our neighbourhood</rs>, which he called his home; and
               where he lived, as much as a love of <placeName ref="#Bath_city">Bath</placeName> and <placeName ref="#Brighton">Brighton</placeName> and <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> and lords would let
               him. He counted many noble families amongst his near connextions, and passed a good
               deal of his time at their country seats—a life for which he was by character and
               habit peculiarly fitted.</p>
            <p>In person he was a tall stout gentlemanly man, <quote>“about fifty, or by’r lady inclining
               to threescore,”</quote><note resp="#sbb #scw">A quotation from <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>'s <title ref="#HenryIVpt1_play">Henry IV Part 1</title>, Act II, scene xi. <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> slightly misquotes the line, which is spoken by <persName ref="#Falstaff_WS">Falstaff</persName> to Prince Hal.</note> with fine features, a composed gravity of countenance and demeanour,
               a bald head most accurately powdered, and a very graceful bow—quite the pattern of an
               elderly man of fashion. His conversation was in excellent keeping with the calm
               imperturbability of his countenance and the sedate gravity of his manner,—smooth,
               dull, common-place, exceedingly safe, and somewhat imposing. He spoke so little, that
               people really fell into the mistake of imagining that he thought; and the tone of
               decision with which he would advance some second-hand opinion, was well calculated to
               confirm the<pb n="180"/> mistake. Gravity was certainly his chief characteristic, and
               yet it was not a clerical gravity either. He had none of the generic marks of his
               profession. Although perfectly decorous in life and word and thought, no stranger
               ever took <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> for a clergyman. He never did any duty any where, that ever I
               heard of, except the agreeable duty of saying grace before dinner; and even that was
               often performed by some lay host, in pure forgetfulness of his guest’s ordination.
               Indeed, but for the direction of his letters, and an eye to <placeName ref="#OldBach_Rectory_OV">* * * Rectory</placeName>, I am
               persuaded that the circumstance might have slipped out of his own recollection.</p>
            <p>His quality of old bachelor was more perceptible. There lurked under all his polish,
               well covered but not concealed, the quiet selfishness, the little whims, the precise
               habits, the primness and priggishness of that disconsolate condition. His man
               <persName ref="#Andrews_OV">Andrews</persName>, for instance, valet, groom, and body-servant abroad; butler, cook, caterer,
               and major domo at home; tall, portly, powdered and black-coated as <rs type="person" ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">his master</rs>, and
               like him in all things but the knowing pig-tail which stuck out horizontally above
               his shirt-collar, giving a ludicrous dignity to his appearance;—<persName ref="#Andrews_OV">Andrews</persName>, who,
               constant as the dial pointed nine, carried up his chocolate and shaving water, and
               regular as <quote>“the chimes at midnight,”</quote><note resp="#sbb">a quotation from <title ref="#Macbeth_play">Macbeth</title></note> prepared his white-wine whey; who never forgot
               his gouty shoe in travelling, (once for two days he<pb n="181"/> had a slight touch
               of that gentlemanly disorder,) and never gave him the newspaper unaired;—to whom
               could <rs type="person" ref="#Andrews_OV">this jewel of a valet</rs>, <rs type="person" ref="#Andrews_OV">this matchless piece of clockwork</rs> belong, but an old
               bachelor? And his little dog <rs type="person" ref="#Viper_pet_OV">Viper</rs>, unparagoned of terriers, black, sleek, sharp, and
               shrewish; who would beg and sneeze and fetch and carry like a Christian; eat olives
               and sweetmeats and mustard, drink coffee and wine and liqueurs;—who but an old
               bachelor could have taught <rs type="person" ref="#Viper_pet_OV">Viper</rs> his multifarious accomplishments?</p>
            <p><rs type="person" ref="#Viper_pet_OV">Little Viper</rs> was a most useful person in his way; for although <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> was a very
               creditable acquaintance to meet on the King's highway,<note resp="#scw">The King's highway refers to the customary public right of way from village to village, even across someone else's property. Source: <bibl corresp="#English_Local_Gov">English Local Government: The Story of the King's Highway.</bibl>.</note>(your dull man, if he rides
               well, should never think of dismounting,) or even on the level ground of a carpet in
               the crowd of a large party; yet when he happened to drop in to take a family dinner—a
               pretty frequent habit of his when in the country—then <rs type="person" ref="#Viper_pet_OV">Viper</rs>’s talents were
               inestimable in relieving the ennui occasioned by that grave piece of gentility <rs type="person" ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">his master</rs>, <quote>“not only dull in himself, but the cause of <emph>dullness</emph> in others.”</quote><note resp="#sbb #scw">Attributed to <persName ref="#Foote_Samuel">Samuel Foote</persName> by <persName ref="#Boswell">Boswell</persName> in <title ref="#Life_Johnson">Life of Johnson</title>.</note> Any thing to
               pass away the heavy hours, till whist or piquet relieved the female world from his
               intolerable silence.</p>
            <p>In other respects these visits were sufficiently perplexing. Every housewife can tell
               what a formidable guest is an epicure who comes to take pot-luck—how sure it is to be
               bad luck, especially when the unfortu-<pb n="182"/>nate hostess lives five miles from
               a market town. <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> always came unseasonably, on washing-day, or Saturday, or
               the day before a great party. So sure as <orgName ref="#OVNarratorsFamily">we</orgName> had a scrap dinner, so sure came he. <persName ref="#OVNarratorsMother">My dear mother</persName>, who with true benevolence and hospitality cared much for her guest’s
               comfort and nothing for her own pride, used to grieve over his discomfiture, and try
               all that could be done by potted meats and omelettes, and little things tossed up on
               a sudden to amend the bill of fare. But cookery is an obstinate art, and will have
               its time;—however you may force the component parts, there is no forcing a dinner.
               <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> had the evil habit of arriving just as the last bell rang; and in spite of
               all the hurry scurry in the kitchen department, the new niceties and the old, homely
               dishes were sure to disagree. There was a total want of keeping. The kickshaws were
               half raw, the solids were mere rags; the vegetables were cold, the soup was scalding:
               no shallots to the rump steaks; no mushrooms with the broiled chicken; no fish; no
               oysters; no ice; no pineapples. Poor <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>! He must have had a great regard for
               us to put up with our bad dinners.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the chance of a rubber had something to do with his visits to our house. If
               there be such a thing as a ruling passion, the love of whist was his. Cards were not
               merely the amusement, but the business of his life. I do not mean as a money-making
                  speculation;<pb n="183"/> for although he belonged to a fashionable club in
               <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>, and to every card-meeting of decent gentility within reach of his country
               home, he never went beyond a regular moderate stake, and could not be induced to bet
               even by the rashest defyer of calculation, or the most provoking undervaluer of his
               play. It always seemed to me that he regarded whist as far too important and
               scientific a pursuit to be degraded into an affair of gambling. It had in his eyes
               all the dignity of a study; an acquirement equally gentlemanly and clerical. It was
               undoubtedly his test of ability. He had the value of a man of family and a man of the
               world, for rank, and wealth, and station, and dignities of all sorts. No human being
               entertained a higher respect for a king, a prince, a prime minister, a duke, a
               bishop, or a lord. But these were conventional feelings. His genuine and unfeigned
               veneration was reserved for him who played a good rubber,<note resp="#scw">A tie-breaking game in a series.</note> a praise he did not easily
               give. He was a capital player himself, and held all his <orgName type="org" ref="#OldBach_whist_competitors_OV">country competitors</orgName>, except
               <rs type="person" ref="#OldBach_Sidney_whist_opponent_OV">one</rs>, in supreme and undisguised contempt, which they endured to admiration. I wonder
               they did not send him to Coventry. He was the most disagreeable partner in the world,
               and nearly as unpleasant an adversary; for he not only enforced the Pythagorean law
               of science, which makes one hate whist so, but used to distribute quite impartially
               to every one at table little disagreeable observations on<pb n="184"/> every card
               they played. It was not scolding, or grumbling, or fretting; one has a sympathy with
               those expressions of feeling, and at the worst can scold again; it was a smooth
               polite commentary on the errors of the party, delivered in the calm tone of undoubted
               superiority with which a great critic will sometimes take a small poet, or a batch of
               poets, to task in a review. How the people could bear it!—but the world is a
               good-natured world, and does not like a man the less for treating it scornfully.</p>
            <p>So passed six evenings out of the seven with <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>; for it was pretty well known
               that, on the rare occurrence of his spending a day at home without company, his
               fac-totum <persName ref="#Andrews_OV">Andrews</persName> used to have the honour of being beaten by his master in a snug
               game at double dumby<note resp="#sbb">A resulting move in the game of bridge when all fifty-two cards can be seen by all the players</note>; but what he did with himself on Sunday occasioned me some
               speculation. Never in my life did I see him take up a book, although he sometimes
               talked of <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> and <persName ref="#Milton">Milton</persName>, and <persName ref="#Johnson">Johnson</persName> and <persName ref="#Burke_E">Burke</persName>, in a manner which proved that
               he had heard of such things; and as to the newspaper, which he did read, that was
               generally conned over long before night; besides he never exhibited spectacles, and I
               have a notion that he could not read newspaper type at night without them. How he
               could possibly get through the after-coffee hours on a Sunday puzzled me long. Chance
               solved the problem. He came to call on <orgName ref="#OVNarratorsFamily">us</orgName> after<pb n="185"/> church, and agreed to
               dine and sleep at our house. The moment tea was over, without the slightest apology
               or attempt at conversation, he drew his chair to the fire, set his feet on the
               fender, and fell fast asleep in the most comfortable and orderly manner possible. It
               was evidently a weekly habit. Every sense and limb seemed composed to it. <rs type="person" ref="#Viper_pet_OV">Viper</rs>
               looked up in his face, curled himself round on the hearth rug, and went to sleep too;
               and <persName ref="#Andrews_OV">Andrews</persName>,just as the clock struck twelve, came in to wake him, that he might go to
               bed. It was clearly an invariable custom; a settled thing.</p>
            <p>His house and grounds were kept in the neatest manner possible. There was something
               even disagreeable in the excessive nicety, the Dutch preciseness of the shining
               gravel walks, the smooth shaven turf of the lawn, and the fine-sifted mould of the
               shrubberies. A few dead leaves or scattered flowers, even a weed or two, any thing to
               take away from the artificial toy-like look of the place, would have been an
               improvement. <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>, however, did not think so. He actually caused his <persName ref="#OldBach_gardener_OV"></persName>gardener
               to remove those littering plants called <rs type="plant" ref="#rose">roses</rs> and <rs type="plant" ref="#cistus">gum cistuses</rs>. Other flowers fared
               little better. No sooner were they in bloom, than <rs type="person" ref="#OldBach_gardener_OV">he</rs> pulled them up for fear they
               should drop. In doors, matters were still worse. The rooms and furniture were very
               handsome, abounding in the luxurious Turkey carpets, the sofas, easy chairs, and
                  ottomans,<pb n="186"/> which his habits required; and yet <persName ref="#OVNarrator">I</persName> never in my life saw
               any house which looked less comfortable. Every thing was so constantly in its place,
               so provokingly in order, so full of naked nicety, so thoroughly old-bachelorish. No
               work! no books! no music! no flowers! But for those two things of life, <rs type="person" ref="#Viper_pet_OV">Viper</rs> and a
               sparkling fire, one might have thought the place uninhabited. Once a year, indeed, it
               gave signs of animation, in the shape of a Christmas party. That was <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>’s
               shining time. Nothing could exceed the smiling hospitality of <rs type="person" ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">the host</rs>, or the lavish
               profusion of the entertainment. It breathed the very spirit of a welcome splendidly
               liberal; and <rs type="person" ref="#Viper_pet_OV">little Viper</rs> frisked and bounded, and <persName ref="#Andrews_OV">Andrews</persName>’s tail vibrated (I was
               going to say wagged) with cordiality and pleasure. <persName ref="#Andrews_OV">Andrews</persName>, on these occasions,
               laid aside his <soCalled>"customary black”</soCalled> in favour of a blue coat and a white silk court
               waistcoat, with a light running pattern of embroidery and silver spangles, assumed to
               do honour to <rs type="person" ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">his master</rs> and <orgName type="org" ref="#OldBach_party_guests_OV">the company</orgName>. How much he enjoyed the applause which the
               wines and the cookery elicited from the <orgName type="org" ref="#OldBach_party_guests_OV">gentlemen</orgName>; and how anxiously he would direct
               the <orgName type="org" ref="#OldBach_party_guests_OV">ladies</orgName>’ attention to a <abbr>MS.</abbr> collection of riddles, the compilation of some
               deceased countess, laid on the drawing-room table for their amusement between dinner
               and tea. Once, I remember, he carried his attention so far as to produce a gone-by
               toy, called a bandalore, for the recreation of<pb n="187"/> <persName ref="#OVNarrator">myself</persName> and another <rs type="person" ref="#OldBach_girl_OV">little
                  girl</rs>, admitted by virtue of the Christmas holidays to this annual festival. Poor
               <persName ref="#Andrews_OV">Andrews</persName>! I am convinced that he considered the entertainment of <rs type="org" ref="#OldBach_party_guests_OV">the visitors</rs> quite as 
                  much his affair as <rs type="person" ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">his master</rs>’s; and certainly they both succeeded. Never did parties 
                  pass more pleasantly. On those evenings <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> even forgot to find fault at whist.
            </p>
            <p>At last, towards the end of a severe winter, during which he had suffered much from
               repeated colds, the <placeName ref="#OldBach_rectory_OV">rectory of * * *</placeName> became vacant, and our worthy neighbour
               hastened to take possession. The day before his journey he called on <rs type="org" ref="#OVNarratorsFamily">us</rs> in the
               highest spirits, anticipating a renewal of health and youth in this favourite spot,
               and approaching nearer than I had ever heard him to a jest on the subject of looking
               out for a wife. Married or single, he made us promise to visit him during the ensuing
               summer. Alas! long before the summer arrived, <rs type="person" ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">our poor friend</rs> was dead. He had waited
               for this living thirty years; he did not enjoy it thirty days.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listPerson sortKey="histPersons">
            <person xml:id="Old_Parr" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Old_Parr">
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname>Parr</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth when="1483">1483
                  <placeName>Alderbury, Shropshire</placeName>
               </birth>
               <death when="1635">1635
               <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName></death>
               <note resp="#sbb #scw">Commonly known as Old Parr, Thomas Parr became something of a celebrity due to his supposed longevity of over 150 years. After his death, an autopsy found that he was likely closer to seventy years old. He is buried in <placeName ref="#Westminster_Abbey">Westminster Abbey</placeName>.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Foote_Samuel" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Foote_Samuel">
                  <forename>Samuel</forename>
                  <surname>Foote</surname>
               </persName>
               <birth when="1720-01">January 1720
                  <placeName>Truro, Cornwall</placeName>
               </birth>
               <death when="1777-10-21">October 21, 1777
               <placeName>Dover</placeName>
               </death>
               <occupation type="theater" subtype="actor"/>
               <occupation type="theater" subtype="manager"/>
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="playwright"/>
               <note resp="#scw">After failing at law and squandering his fortune, Samuel Foote became an actor on the <placeName ref="#Dublin">Dublin</placeName> and <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> stages, noted for his skills in mimicry, which he used to mock fellow actors and other celebrities. He acted at <placeName ref="#Drury_Lane_Theatre">Drury Lane</placeName> (where he was joint-manager) and  <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Covent Garden</placeName>. He succeeded in gaining a lease on <placeName ref="#Haymarket_Theatre">the Haymarket Theater</placeName>, where he performed his own works of mimicry, which he styled <q>"teas"</q> to avoid licensing laws. The bulk of his theatrical works are satirical plays, often provoking to his contemporaries, particularly <persName ref="#Fielding_Henry">Henry Fielding</persName>. Nevertheless, he earned the admiration of <persName ref="#Johnson">Johnson</persName>, and the cautious friendship of <persName ref="#Garrick_David">David Garrick</persName>.</note>
               <note><ref target="http://viaf.org/viaf/29561715"/></note>
            </person>

         </listPerson>
         
            <listPerson sortKey="fictPersons">
               <person xml:id="Sidney_Mr_OV" sex="m">
                  <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney
                     <forename>Not given</forename>
                     <surname>Sidney</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <occupation type="religious" subtype="curate"/>
                  <occupation type="educator"/>        
                  <note resp="#sbb #scw">The main character of <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
               </person>
           
               <person xml:id="Andrews_OV" sex="m">
                  <persName ref="#Andrews_OV">Andrews
                     <forename>Not given</forename>
                     <surname>Andrews</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <occupation type="service" subtype="majordomo"/>
                  <occupation type="service" subtype="cook"/>
                  <note resp="#sbb #scw">Character who serves as the main servant to <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>'s in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>, and acts on behalf of the household owner.</note>
               </person>
          
               <person xml:id="OldBach_gardener_OV" sex="m">
                  <persName ref="#OldBach_gardener_OV">
                     <forename>Not given</forename>
                     <surname>Not given</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <note resp="#sbb #scw">Character of the gardener to <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>, who appears in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="OldBach_girl_OV" sex="f">
               <persName ref="#OldBach_girl_OV">girl at party in An Old Bachelor
                  <forename>Not given</forename>
                  <surname>Not given</surname>
               </persName>
                  <note resp="#scw">A young girl mentioned in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title> who attends <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>'s Christmas parties along with <persName ref="#OVNarrator">the narrator</persName> when she was a child.</note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="OldBach_incumbent_OV" sex="m">
                  <persName ref="#OldBach_incumbent_OV">Old Bachelor incumbent
                  <forename>Not given</forename>
                  <surname>Not given</surname>   
                  </persName>
                  <occupation type="religious" subtype="curate"/>
                  <note resp="#scw">Character of the long-lived occupant of <placeName ref="#OldBach_Rectory_OV">the unnamed rectory</placeName>that <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> is waiting to occupy in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="OldBach_Sidney_whist_opponent_OV" sex="u">
                  <persName ref="#OldBach_Sidney_whist_opponent_OV">Mr. Sidney's whist opponent
                     <forename>Not given</forename>
                     <surname>Not given</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <note resp="#scw">A significant opponent of <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> at whist in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
               </person>
               
               <person xml:id="OldBach_young_visitor_OV" sex="u">
                  <persName ref="#OldBach_young_visitor_OV">young visitor in An Old Bachelor
                     <forename>Not given</forename>
                     <surname>Not given</surname>
                  </persName>
                  <note resp="#scw">Character who is visiting the <orgName ref="#OVNarratorsFamily">Our Village narrator's family</orgName> when the story of <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> is told in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
               </person>
               
               
               
               <person xml:id="Viper_pet_OV" sex="m">
                  <persName ref="#Viper_pet_OV">Viper</persName>
                  <note resp="#sbb"><persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>'s pet terrier in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
               </person>
               
            </listPerson>
         
            <listPlace sortKey="fictPlaces">
               <place xml:id="OldBach_Rectory_OV">
                  <placeName ref="#OldBach_Rectory_OV">Rectory in An Old Bachelor</placeName>
                  <note resp="#scw">The unnamed rectory that <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> waits most of his adult life to occupy in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
               </place>
               
               <place xml:id="OldBach_college_OV">
                  <placeName ref="#OldBach_college_OV">* * College in An Old Bachelor</placeName>
                  <note resp="#scw">The unnamed College where <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>is a fellow while awaiting a vacancy at <placeName ref="#OldBach_Rectory_OV">the unnamed rectory</placeName> in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         
         
           <listOrg sortKey="fictOrgs"><!--scw: integrate into si-add fictional people OV file-->
               <org xml:id="OVNarratorsFamily">
               <orgName ref="#OVNarratorsFamily">OV Narrator's nuclear family</orgName>
               <note resp="#sbb #scw">The nuclear family of the <persName ref="#OVNarrator">Our Village narrator</persName>, which consists of herself, her father, and her mother, closely mirroring <orgName ref="#Mitfords">the Mitfords</orgName>. The family is not always directly specified, and will often be referred to as <q>"we"</q> and <q>"our"</q> when the narrator speaks.</note>
               </org>
              
              <org xml:id="OldBach_whist_competitors_OV"><orgName ref="#OldBach_whist_competitors_OV">competitors of Mr. Sidney at whist</orgName>
                 <note resp="#scw">The assorted characters with whom <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName> plays whist in <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
              </org>
              
              <org xml:id="OldBach_party_guests_OV">
                 <orgName ref="#OldBach_party_guests_OV">party guests of Mr. Sidney</orgName>
                 <note resp="#scw">Guests at the annual Christmas party of <persName ref="#Sidney_Mr_OV">Mr. Sidney</persName>, the protagonist of <title level="a" ref="#Old_Bachelor_OV">An Old Bachelor</title>.</note>
              </org>
            </listOrg>
            
            <listBibl sortKey="schol">
               
               <bibl xml:id="English_Local_Gov">
                  <title ref="#English_Local_Gov">English Local Government: The Story of the King's Highway</title>
                  <author>Sidney Webb</author>
                  <author>Beatrice Webb</author>
                  <publisher>Longman, Green &amp; Co.</publisher>
                  <date when="1913">1913</date>
               </bibl>
               
               <bibl xml:id="Life_Johnson">
                  <title ref="#Life_Johnson">Life of Samuel Johnson, L.L.D.</title>
                  <author>James Boswell</author>
                  <publisher>Charles Dilly</publisher>
                  <date>1791</date>
                  <note resp="#scw">Influential and controversial biography of <persName ref="#Johnson">Samuel Johnson</persName> that came to set a standard for life-writing in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.</note>
               </bibl>
               
               
            </listBibl>
        
         <list sortKey="plants">
            
            
            <item xml:id="rose"></item><!--scw 7/27/22: in SI but not being picked up-->
         </list>
            
           
         
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
