<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng"
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng" 
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>


            <titleStmt>
                <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
                <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>

                <editor ref="#ad">Alexandra Drayton</editor>
                <editor ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</editor>


                <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
                    Project</orgName></sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#ad">Alexandra Drayton</persName>
                    <persName ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName ref="#bas">Brooke A. Stewart</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain
                    phrases describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date:
                    2 June 2013. P5.</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
                    <persName>Who?</persName>
                </respStmt>

            </editionStmt>



            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
                        Unported License</licence>
                </availability>

            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
            </seriesStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
                <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
                <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                        <title ref="#OV">Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and
                            Scenery</title><edition>Third Edition</edition> by <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell
                            Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher ref="#Whittaker_GB_pub">Geo. B.
                            Whittaker</publisher><placeName ref="#AveMariaLane">Ave Maria
                            Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>. </bibl> This text appears to be
                    identical in pagination and content to the first edition published in 1824. </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <pb n="ii"/>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Our Village:</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="subtitle">Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>by <docAuthor>Mary Russell Mitford</docAuthor>, Author of <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian, A
                        Tragedy</title><lb/></byline>
                <docEdition>Third Edition.</docEdition>
                <docImprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><lb/><publisher>Geo. B.
                        Whittaker</publisher>,<lb/><placeName ref="#AveMariaLane">Ave-Maria-Lane</placeName>.
                        <docDate>1825</docDate>.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb n="iii"/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="sketch">
                <head><title level="a" ref="#Mod_Antiques_OV">MODERN ANTIQUES.</title></head>
                <p>Early in the <date from="1801" to="1900">present century</date> there lived in the ancient town of <placeName ref="#B_city_OV">B.</placeName> two complete
                    and remarkable specimens of the ladies of <time dur="P80Y">eighty years</time> ago—ladies cased inwardly
                    and outwardly in <persName ref="#Addison_Joseph">Addison</persName> and whalebone. How they had been preserved in this
                    entireness, amidst the collision and ridicule of a country town, seemed as
                    puzzling a question as the preservation of bees in amber, or mummies in
                    pyramids, or any other riddle that serves to amuse the naturalist or the
                    antiquarian. But so it was. They were <rs type="person" ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV #Theodosia_Mrs_OV">old maids and sisters</rs>, and so alike in
                    their difference from all other women, that they may be best described together;
                    any little non-resemblance may be noted afterwards; it was no more than nature,
                    prodigal of variety, would make in two leaves from the same oak-tree.</p>
                <p>Both, then, were as short as women well could be without being entitled to the
                    name of dwarf, or carried about to fairs for a show;—both were made considerably
                    shorter by the highest of all high heels, and the<pb n="37"/> tallest of all
                    tall caps, each of which artificial elevations was as ostentatiously conspicuous
                    as the legs and cover of a pipkin, and served equally to add to the squatness of
                    the real machine; both were lean, wrinkled, withered, and old; both enveloped
                    their aged persons in the richest silks, displayed over large hoops, and stays
                    the tightest and stiffest that ever pinched in a beauty of <persName ref="#GeoII">George the Second</persName>’s
                    reign. The gown was of that make formerly, I believe, called a sacque<note resp="#scw">A <soCalled>sack-back gown</soCalled>, also known as a <emph rend="italics"><foreign xml:lang="fr">robe a la francaise</foreign></emph>, was a style of gown that was unfitted at the back and consequently hung down from the neck to the feet.</note>, and of a
                    pattern so enormous, that one flower, with its stalk and leaves, would nearly
                    cover the three quarters of a yard in length, of which the tail might, at a
                    moderate computation, consist. Over this they wore a gorgeously figured apron,
                    whose flourishing white embroidery vied in size with the plants on the robe; a
                    snowy muslin neckerchief, rigidly pinned down; and over that a black lace tippet
                    of the same shape, parting at the middle, to display a gay breast-knot. The
                    riband of which this last decoration was composed was generally the same which adorned the towering lappeted cap, a sort of poppy colour, which
                    they called Pompadour. The sleeves were cut off below the elbows with triple
                    ruffles of portentous length. Brown leather mittens, with peaks turned back, and
                    lined with blue satin, and a variety of tall rings in an odd, out-of-fashion
                    variety of enamelling, and figures of hair,<pb n="38"/> completed the decoration
                    of their hands and arms. The carriage of these <rs type="person" ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV #Theodosia_Mrs_OV">useful members</rs> was at least
                    equally singular; they had adapted themselves in a remarkable manner to the
                    little taper wasp-like point in which the waist ended, to which the elbows,
                    ruffles and all, adhered as closely as if they had been glued, whilst the ringed
                    and mittened hands, when not employed in knitting, were crossed saltier-wise, in
                    front of the apron. The other termination of their figure was adorned with black
                    stuff shoes, very peaked, with points upwards, and massive silver buckles. Their
                    walking costume was, in winter, a black silk cloak, lined with rabbit-skins,
                    with holes for the arms; in summer, another tippet and a calash,—no bonnet could
                    hold the turreted cap. Their motion out of doors was indescribable; it most
                    nearly resembled sailing. They seemed influenced by the wind in a way incidental
                    to no moving thing, except a ship or a shuttlecock; and, indeed, one boisterous
                    blowing night, about the equinox, when standing on some high stone steps,
                    waiting for a carriage to take her home from a party, the wind did catch one of
                    them, and, but for the intervention of a tall <persName ref="#ModAntiques_tallFootman_OV">footman</persName>, who seized her as one
                    would seize a flyaway umbrella, and held her down by main force, the poor little
                    lady would have been carried up like an air-balloon. Her feelings must have been
                    pretty much si-<pb n="39"/>milar to those of <persName ref="#Gulliver">Gulliver</persName> in <placeName ref="#Brobdingnag">Brobdignag</placeName>, when flown
                        away with by the eagle. Half a minute later, and she was gone.<note resp="#scw">Refers to the sequence in which <persName ref="#Gulliver">Gulliver</persName> escapes <placeName ref="#Brobdingnag">Brobdingnag</placeName> by being carried off by an eagle.</note></p>
                <p>So far they were exact counterparts. The chief variation lay in the face. Amidst
                    the general hue of age and wrinkles, you could just distinguish that <persName ref="#Theodosia_Mrs_OV">Mrs.
                        Theodosia</persName> had been brown, and <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Mrs.Frances</persName> fair. There was a yellow shine here
                    and there amongst the white hairs, curiously rolled over a cushion high above
                    the forehead, that told of <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Fanny</persName>’s golden locks; whilst the purely grey rouleau
                    of <persName ref="#Theodosia_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Theodosia</persName> showed its mixture of black and white still plainer. <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Mrs.
                        Frances</persName>, too, had the blue eye, with a laughing light, which so often retains
                    its flash to extreme age; whilst <persName ref="#Theodosia_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Theodosia</persName>’s orbs, bright no longer, had
                    once been hazel. <persName ref="#Theodosia_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Theodosia</persName>’s aquiline nose, and long sociable chin, evinced
                    that disposition to meet which is commonly known by the name of a pair of
                    nut-crackers; <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Frances</persName>’ features, on the other hand, were rather tense and
                    sharp. Still there was, in spite of these material differences, that look of
                    kindred, that inexplicable and indefinable family likeness, which is so
                    frequently found in sisters; greatly increased in the present case by a
                    similarity in the voice that was quite startling. Both tongues were quick and
                    clear, and high and rattling, to a degree that seemed rather to belong to
                    machinery than to human articulation; and<pb n="40"/> when welcomes and
                    how-d’ye-dos were pouring both at once on either side, a stranger was apt to
                    gaze in ludicrous perplexity, as if beset by a ventriloquist, or haunted by
                    strange echoes. When the immediate cackle subsided, they were easily
                    distinguished. <persName ref="#Theodosia_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Theodosia</persName> was good, and kind, and hospitable, and social;
                    <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Frances</persName> was all that, and was besides shrewd, and clever, and literary, to
                    a degree not very common in her day, though not approaching to the pitch of a
                    blue-stocking lady of the present. Accident was partly the cause of this unusual
                    love of letters. They had known <persName ref="#Richardson_Sam">Richardson</persName>; had been admitted amongst his
                    flower-garden of young ladies; and still talked familiarly of <persName ref="#Highmore_Susanna">Miss Highmore</persName>,
                    <persName ref="#Fielding_Sarah">Miss Fielding</persName>, <persName ref="#Collier_Margaret">Miss Collier</persName>, and <persName ref="#Chapone_Hester">Miss Mulso</persName>,—they had never learned to call her
                    <persName ref="#Chapone_Hester">>Mrs. Chapone</persName>. Latterly the taste had been renewed and quickened, by their having
                    the honour of a distant relationship to one of the most amiable and unfortunate
                    of modern poets.<note resp="#scw">This <q>amiable and unfortunate</q> poet has yet to be identified.</note><!--scw: find out who this modern poet might be--> <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Frances</persName> studied novels and poetry, in addition to <rs type="person" ref="#Theodosia_Mrs_OV">her
                        sister</rs>’s sermons and cookery-books; though (as she used to boast) without doing
                    a stitch the less of knitting, or playing a pool the fewer in the course of the
                    year. Their usual occupations were those of other useful old ladies;
                    superintending the <orgName ref="#endowedGirlsSchool_OV">endowed girls’ school</orgName> <!--scw 6/26/23: endowed girls' school must be the one in Reading. Check and add to SI note.-->of the town with a vigilance and a
                    jealousy of abuses that might have done the honour to <persName ref="#hume">Mr. Hume</persName>;<!--scw: The context of this statement makes David Hume questionable as the identification here.--> taking an active
                    part in the<pb n="41"/> more private charities, donations of flannel petticoats,
                    or the loan of baby-things; visiting in a quiet way; and going to church
                    whenever the church door was open.</p>
                <p>Their abode was a dwelling ancient and respectable, like themselves, that looked
                    as if it had never undergone the slightest variation, inside or out, since they
                    had been born in it. The rooms were many, low and small; full of little windows
                    with little panes, and chimneys stuck perversely in the corners. The furniture
                    was exactly to correspond; little patches of carpets in the middle of the
                    slippery, dry-rubbed floors; tables and chairs of mahogany, black with age, but
                    exceedingly neat and bright; and Japan cabinets and old China, which <persName ref="#Beckford_William">Mr.
                        Beckford</persName> might have envied—treasures which had either never gone out of fashion,
                    or had come in again. The garden was beautiful and beautifully placed; a series
                    of terraces descending to rich and finely timbered meadows, through which the
                    slow magnificent <placeName ref="#Thames">Thames</placeName> rolled under the fine chalky hills of the pretty <placeName ref="#C_vil_OV">village of
                        C.</placeName><!--scw 6/26/23: identify village of C. Is it the same as the one mentioned in "Thaw"? I made an SI-ID for it, suggesting it might be Caversham based on certain textual evidence, but did not link to "Thaw". Still need to check out the info regarding the old friary wall. --> It was bounded on one side by the remains of an old friary, the end wall of a
                    chapel with a Gothic window of open tracery in high preservation, as rich as
                    point lace. It was full too of old-fashioned durable flowers, <name ref="#jessamine">jessamine</name>,
                    <name ref="#honeysuckle">honeysuckle</name>, and the high-scented <name ref="#fraxinella">fraxinella</name>; I never saw that delicious plant
                    in such profusion. The garden-walks were<pb n="42"/> almost as smooth as the
                    floors, thanks to the two assiduous <persName ref="#Mod_Antiques_servingMaid1_OV #Mod_Antiques_servingMaid2_OV">serving maidens</persName> (nothing like a man servant
                    ever entered this maidenly abode) who attended it. One, the <persName ref="#Mod_Ant_ServingMaid1_OV">under damsel</persName>, was a
                    stout strapping country wench, changed from time to time as it happened; <persName ref="#Mod_Ant_ServingMaid2_OV">the
                        other</persName> was as much a fixture as <rs type="person" ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV #Theodosia_Mrs_OV">her mistresses</rs>. She had lived with them for <time dur="P40Y">forty
                            years</time>, and, except being twice as big and twice as tall, might have passed for
                    another sister. She wore their gowns, (the two just made her one,) caps,
                    ruffles, and aprons; talked with their voices and their phrases; followed them
                    to church, and school, and market; scolded the school-mistress; heard the
                    children their catechism; cut out flannel petticoats, and knit stockings to give
                    away. Never was so complete an instance of assimilation! She had even become
                    like them in face.</p>
                <p>Having <persName ref="#ModAntiques_sistersBrother_OV">a brother</persName> who resided at a beautiful seat in the neighbourhood, and being
                    to all intents and purposes of the patrician order, their visitors were very
                    select, and rather more from the country than the town. Six formed the general
                    number,—one table—a rubber or a pool—seldom more. As the only child of a very
                    favourite friend, <persName ref="#OVNarrator">I</persName> used, during the holidays, to be admitted as a
                    supernumerary; at first out of compliment to <persName ref="#OVNarratorsMother">mamma</persName>; latterly I stood on my own
                    merits. I was found to be a <rs type="person" ref="#OVNarrator">quiet little girl</rs>; an excellent hander of muffins
                    and cake; a connoisseur in green tea; an ama-<pb n="43"/>teur of quadrille—the
                    most entertaining of all games to a looker-on; and, lastly and chiefly, a great
                    lover and admirer of certain books, which filled two little shelves at
                    cross corners with the chimney—namely, that volume of <persName ref="#Cowper">Cowper</persName>’s <title level="a" ref="#TheTask_WC">Poems</title> which
                        contained <title level="a" ref="#John_Gilpin_poem">John Gilpin</title>, and the whole seven volumes of <title level="m" ref="#Chas_Grandison_novel">Sir Charles Grandison</title>.
                    With what delight I used to take down those dear books! It was an old
                    edition;—perhaps that very first edition which, as <persName ref="#BarbauldAL">Mrs. Barbauld</persName> says, the fine
                    ladies used to hold up to one another at <placeName ref="#Ranelagh">Ranelagh</placeName>,<note resp="#scw"><!--scw 6/26/23: find the source of this--></note>—and adorned with prints, not
                    certainly of the highest merit as works of art, but which served exceedingly to
                    realise the story, and to make us, as it were, personally acquainted with the
                    characters. The costume was pretty much that of <rs type="person" ref="#Theodosia_Mrs_OV #Frances_Mrs_OV">my worthy hostesses</rs>, especially
                    that of the <persName ref="#Selby_Lucy_SR #Selby_Nancy_SR">two Miss Selbys</persName>; there was even in <persName ref="#Selby_Nancy_SR">Miss Nancy</persName>’s face a certain
                        likeness to <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Frances</persName>. I remember I used to wonder whether she carried her
                    elbows in the same way. How I read and believed, and believed and read; and
                    liked <persName ref="#Lady_G_SR">lady G.</persName> though I thought her naughty; and gave all my wishes to <persName ref="#Byron_Harriet_SR">Harriet</persName>,
                    though I thought her silly; and loved <persName ref="#Jervois_Emily_SR">Emily</persName> with my whole heart! <persName ref="#Clementina_SR">Clementina</persName> I
                    did not quite understand; nor (I am half afraid to say so) do I now; and <persName ref="#Chas_Grandison_fict">Sir
                    Charles</persName> I positively disliked. He was the only thing in the book that I
                        disbelieved. Those bowings seemed incredible. At last, however, I extended my
                    faith even to him;<pb n="44"/> partly influenced by the irresistibility of <rs type="person" ref="#Richardson_Sam">the
                        author</rs>, partly by the appearance of a real <persName ref="#ModAntiquesBeau_OV">living beau</persName>, who in the matter of
                    bowing might almost have competed with <persName ref="#Chas_Grandison_fict">Sir Charles</persName> himself. This <persName ref="#ModAntiquesBeau_OV">beau</persName> was no
                    other than the town member, who, with <persName ref="#ModAntiquesBrother_OV">his brother</persName>, was, when in the country, the
                    constant attendant at these chosen parties.</p>
                <p><persName ref="#ModAntiquesBeau_OV">Our member</persName> was a man of seventy, or thereabout, but wonderfully young-looking
                    and well-preserved. It was said, indeed, that no fading belle was better versed
                    in cosmetic secrets, or more devoted to the duties of the toilet. Fresh,
                    upright, unwrinkled, pearly-teethed, and point device in his accoutrements, he
                    might have passed for fifty; and doubtless often did pass for such when apart
                    from his old-looking younger <persName ref="#ModAntiquesBrother_OV">brother</persName>; who, tall, lanky, shambling, long-visaged,
                    and loosely dressed, gave a very vivid idea of <persName ref="#Don_Quixote_char">Don Quixote</persName>, when stripped of his
                    armour. Never was so consummate a courtier as our <persName ref="#ModAntiquesBeau_OV">member</persName>! Of good family and
                    small fortune, he had early in life been seized with the desire of representing
                    the <rs type="place" ref="#B_city_OV">town in which he resided</rs>;<!--scw 6/26/23: Be sure to re-check to make sure this is indeed B_city--> and canvassing, sheer canvassing, without
                    eloquence, without talent, without bribery, had brought him in and kept him in.
                    There his ambition stopped. To be a member of parliament was with him not the
                    means but the end of advancement. For <time dur="P40Y">forty years</time> he represented an
                    independent<pb n="45"/> borough, and, though regularly voting with every
                    successive ministry, was, at the end of his career, as poor as when he began. He
                    never sold himself, or stood suspected of selling himself—perhaps he might
                    sometimes give himself away. But that he could not help. It was almost
                    impossible for him to say No to any body,—quite so to a minister, or a
                    constituent, or a constituent’s wife or daughter. So he passed bowing and
                    smiling through the world, the most disinterested of courtiers, the most
                    subservient of upright men, with little other annoyance than a <time dur="P7Y">septennial</time>
                    alarm,—for sometimes an opposition was threatened, and sometimes it came; <!--scw 6/26/23: Consider annotating this Parliamentary business-->but
                    then he went through a double course of smirks and hand-shakings, and all was
                    well again. The great grievance of his life must have been the limitation in the
                    number of franks. His apologies, when he happened to be full, were such as a man
                    would make for a great fault; his lamentations, such as might become a great
                    misfortune. Of course there was something ludicrous in his courtliness, but it
                    was not contemptible; it only wanted to be obviously disinterested to become
                    respectable. The expression might be exaggerated; but the feeling was real. He
                    was always ready to show kindness to the utmost of his power to any human being.
                    He would have been just as civil and supple if he had not<pb n="46"/> been <abbr>M.P.</abbr>
                    It was his vocation. He could not help it.</p>
                <p>This <rs type="person" ref="#ModAntiquesBeau_OV">excellent person</rs> was an old bachelor; and there was a rumour, some <time dur="P40Y">forty</time> or
                    <time dur="P50Y">fifty years</time> old, that in the days of their bloom, there had been a little love
                    affair, an attachment, some even said an engagement, how broken none could tell,
                    between him and <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Frances</persName>. Certain it is, that there were symptoms of
                    flirtation still. His courtesy, always gallant to every female, had something
                    more real and more tender towards <quote><soCalled><persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Fanny</persName></soCalled>,</quote> as he was wont to call her; and
                    <persName ref="#Frances_Mrs_OV">Fanny</persName>, on her side, was as conscious as heart could desire. She blushed and
                    bridled; fidgeted with her mittens or her apron; flirted a fan nearly as tall as
                    herself, and held her head on one side with that peculiar air which I have noted
                    in the shyer birds, and ladies in love. She manoeuvred to get him next her at
                    the tea-table; liked to be his partner at whist; loved to talk of him in his
                    absence; knew to an hour the time of his return; and did not dislike a little
                    gentle raillery on the subject—even <persName ref="#OVNarrator">I</persName>—But, traitress to my sex, how can I jest
                    with such feelings? Rather let me sigh over the world of woe, that in <time dur="P50Y">fifty
                        years</time> of hopeless constancy must have passed through that maiden heart! The
                    timid hope; the sickening suspense; the slow, slow fear; the bitter
                        disappointment;<pb n="47"/> the powerless anger; the relenting; the
                    forgiveness; and then again, that interest, kinder, truer, more unchanging than
                    friendship, that lingering woman’s love—Oh how can I jest over such feelings?
                    They are passed away—for she is gone, and he—but they clung by her to the last,
                    and ceased only in death.<pb n="48"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
          <div></div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
