<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng"
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng" 
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <!--MAH: June 20th:: This piece as well as THAW appear to be two parts of the same sketch, “Walks in the Country,” I have them as two separate pieces, unsure how we’ll want to show them later, but they should be relatively easy to combine. There will be a similar note in THAW to show that they are tied together.-->
            <!--SW: July 8, 2013: Thanks for noting!-->
            
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
                <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>
                <editor ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</editor>
                <editor ref="#ad" >Alexandra Drayton</editor>
               
                
                
                <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
                    Project</orgName></sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName>Alexandra Drayton</persName>
                    <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName ref="#bas">Brooke A. Stewart</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
                    describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
                    P5.</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
                    <persName>Who?</persName>
                </respStmt>
                
            </editionStmt>
            
            
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                        License</licence>
                </availability>
                
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <notesStmt>
                <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
                <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
                <p>Our text is based on  public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                    <title level="m" ref="#OV">Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B. Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
                </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first edition published in 1824.  
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        
        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <pb n="ii"/>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Our Village:</titlePart><titlePart type="subtitle">Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>by <docAuthor>Mary Russell Mitford</docAuthor>, Author of <title level="m" ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian, A Tragedy</title><lb/></byline>
                <docEdition>Third Edition.</docEdition>
                <docImprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><lb/><publisher>Geo. B. Whittaker</publisher>,<lb/><placeName ref="#AveMariaLane">Ave-Maria-Lane</placeName>.
                    <docDate>1825</docDate>.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb n="iii"/>
        </front><body>
            <div type="sketch">
                <head><title level="s" ref="#Walks_Country_OV"></title>WALKS IN THE COUNTRY.<lb/><title level="a" ref="#Walks_Frost_Thaw_OV"></title>FROST.</head> 
                <p><date when="--01-23">January 23d.</date>—At <time when="12:00:00">noon</time> to-day <persName ref="#OVNarrator">I</persName> and my white greyhound, <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May-flower</persName>, set out for a walk into a very beautiful world,—a sort of silent fairy-land,—a creation of that matchless magician the hoar-frost. There had been just snow enough to cover the earth and all its colours with one sheet of pure and uniform white, and just time enough since the snow had fallen to allow the hedges to be freed of their fleecy load, and clothed with a delicate coating of rime. The atmosphere was deliciously calm; soft, almost mild, in spite of the thermometer; no perceptible air, but a stillness that might almost be felt; the sky, rather grey than blue, throwing out in bold relief the snow-covered roofs of <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">our village,</placeName> and the rimy trees that rise above them; and the sun shining dimly as through a veil, giving a pale fair light, like the moon, only brighter. There was a silence, too, that might become the moon, as we stood<pb n="28"/> at our little gate looking up the quiet street; a sabbath-like pause of work and play, rare on a work-day: nothing was audible but the pleasant hum of frost, that low monotonous sound, which is perhaps the nearest approach that life and nature can make to silence. The very waggons as they come down the hill along the beaten track of crisp yellowish frost-dust, glide along like shadows; even <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>s’ bounding footsteps, at her height of glee and of speed, fall like snow upon snow. </p>
                <p>But we shall have noise enough presently: <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName> has stopped at <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Lizzy</persName>’s door; and <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Lizzy</persName>, as she sate on the window-sill, with her bright rosy face laughing through the casement, has seen her and disappeared. She is coming. No! The key is turning in the door, and sounds of evil omen issue through the key-hole—sturdy <said who="#Lizzy_OV" direct="false">let-me-outs,</said><!--scw: single quotation marks in the text--> and <said who="#Lizzy_OV" direct="false">I-will-gos,</said> mixed with shrill cries on <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName> and on me from <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Lizzy</persName>, piercing through a low continuous harangue, of which the prominent parts are apologies, chilblains, sliding, broken bones, lollypops, rods, and gingerbread, from <persName ref="#LizzysMother_OV">Lizzy’s careful mother</persName>. <said who="#OVNarrator" direct="true">Don’t scratch the door, <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>! Don’t roar so, my <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Lizzy</persName>! We’ll call for you as we come back.</said>— <said who="#Lizzy_OV" direct="true">I’ll go now! Let me out; I will go!</said> are the last words of <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Miss Lizzy</persName>. <abbr>Mem.</abbr> Not to spoil that <rs type="person" ref="#Lizzy_OV">child</rs>—if I can help it. But I do think <rs type="person" ref="#LizzysMother_OV">her mother</rs> might have let the <rs type="person" ref="#Lizzy_OV">poor little soul</rs> walk with us to-day. No<pb n="29"/>thing worse for children than coddling. Nothing better for chilblains than exercise. Besides, I don’t believe she has any—and as to breaking her bones in sliding, I don’t suppose there’s a slide on the common. These murmuring cogitations have brought us up the hill, and half-way across the light and airy common, with its bright expanse of snow and its clusters of cottages, whose turf fires send such wreaths of smoke sailing up the air, and diffusing such aromatic fragrance around. And now comes the delightful sound of childish voices, ringing with glee and merriment almost from beneath our feet. Ah, <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Lizzy</persName>, <persName ref="#LizzysMother_OV">your mother</persName> was right! They are shouting from that deep irregular pool, all glass now, where, on two long, smooth, liny slides, half a dozen ragged <orgName type="person" ref="#sliding_urchins_OV">urchins</orgName> are slipping along in tottering triumph. Half a dozen steps bring us to the bank right above them. <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName> can hardly resist the temptation of joining her friends, for most of the <orgName type="person" ref="#sliding_urchins_OV">varlets</orgName> are of her acquaintance, especially the <rs type="person" ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">rogue</rs> who leads the slide,—he with the brimless hat, whose bronzed complexion and white flaxen hair, reversing the usual lights and shadows of the human countenance, give so strange and foreign a look to his flat and comic features. This <rs type="person" ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">hobgoblin</rs>, <persName type="fict" ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">Jack Rapley</persName> by name, is <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>’s great crony; and she stands on the brink of the steep irregular descent, her black eyes fixed full upon him, as if she intended him the favour of jumping on his head. She<pb n="30"/> does: she is down, and upon him: but <persName ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">Jack Rapley</persName> is not easily to be knocked off his feet. He saw her coming, and in the moment of her leap sprang dexterously off the slide on the rough ice, steadying himself by the shoulder of the next in the file, which unlucky follower, thus unexpectedly checked in his career, fell plump backwards, knocking down the rest of the line like a nest of card-houses. There is no harm done; but there they lie roaring, kicking, sprawling, in every attitude of comic distress, whilst <persName ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">Jack Rapley</persName> and <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May-flower,</persName> sole authors of this calamity, stand apart from the throng, fondling, and coquetting, and complimenting each other, and very visibly laughing, <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName> in her black eyes, <persName ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">Jack</persName> in his wide close-shut mouth, and his whole monkey-face, at <orgName type="person" ref="#sliding_urchins_OV">their comrades</orgName>’ mischances. I think, <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">Miss May</persName>, you may as well come up again, and leave <persName ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">Master Rapley</persName> to fight your battles. He’ll get out of the scrape. He is a <rs type="person" ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">rustic wit</rs>—a sort of <persName ref="#Robin_Goodfellow">Robin Goodfellow</persName>—the sauciest, idlest, cleverest, best-natured boy in the <placeName ref="#Shinfield_parish">parish</placeName>; always foremost in mischief, and always ready to do a good turn. The sages of our village predict sad things of <persName ref="#Rapley_Jack_OV">Jack Rapley</persName>, so that I am sometimes a little ashamed to confess, before wise people, that I have a lurking predilection for him, (in common with other naughty ones), and that I like to hear him talk to <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName> almost as well as she does. <said who="#OVNarrator">Come, <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>!</said><!--scw 6/21/23: Single quotation marks used here--> and up she springs, as light as a bird.<pb n="31"/> The road is gay now; carts and post-chaises, and <orgName type="person" ref="#redCloakGirls_OV">girls in red cloaks</orgName>, and, afar off, looking almost like a toy, the coach. It meets us fast and soon. How much happier the <orgName type="person" ref="#walkers_OV">walkers</orgName> look than the <orgName type="person" ref="#riders_OV">riders</orgName>—especially the <rs type="person" ref="#frost_bitten_gent_OV">frostbitten gentleman,</rs> and the <rs type="person" ref="#shivering_lady_OV">shivering lady</rs> with the invisible face, sole passengers of that commodious machine! Hooded, veiled, and bonneted as she is, one sees from her attitude how miserable she would look uncovered.</p>
                <p>Another pond, and another noise of children. More sliding? Oh! no. This is a sport of higher pretension. Our good neighbour, the <persName ref="#Lieutenant_OV">lieutenant</persName>, <sic>skaiting</sic>,<!--scw: The OED lists various spellings in use in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, including the one used by MRM here.--> and his own <orgName type="person" ref="#Lieutenants_children_OV">pretty little boys</orgName>, and two or three other <orgName type="person" ref="#skating_spectators_OV">four-year-old elves</orgName>, standing on the brink in an ecstasy of joy and wonder! Oh what happy <orgName type="person" ref="#skating_spectators_OV">spectators</orgName>! And what a happy <rs type="person" ref="#Lieutenant_OV">performer</rs>! They admiring, he admired, with ardour and sincerity never excited by all the quadrilles and the spread eagles of the <placeName ref="#Seine_river">Seine</placeName> and the <placeName ref="#Serpentine">Serpentine</placeName>, He really skaites well though, and I am glad I came this way; for, with all the <rs type="person" ref="#Lieutenant_OV">father</rs>’s feelings sitting gaily at his heart, it must still gratify the pride of skill to have one spectator at that solitary pond who has seen skaiting before.</p>
                <p>Now we have reached the trees,—the beautiful trees! never so beautiful as to-day. Imagine the effect of a straight and regular double avenue of <name ref="#oak">oaks</name>, nearly a mile long, arching over head, and closing into perspec<pb n="32"/>tive like the roof and columns of a cathedral, every tree and branch encrusted with the bright and delicate congelation of hoar-frost, white and pure as snow, delicate and defined as carved ivory. How beautiful it is, how uniform, how various, how filling, how satiating to the eye and to the mind—above all, how melancholy! There is a thrilling awfulness, an intense feeling of simple power in that naked and colourless beauty, which falls on the heart like the thought of death—death pure, and glorious, and smiling,—but still death. Sculpture has always the same effect on my imagination, and painting never. Colour is life.—We are now at the end of this magnificent avenue, and at the top of a steep eminence commanding a wide view over four counties—a landscape of snow. A deep lane leads abruptly down the hill; a mere narrow cart-track, sinking between high banks clothed with <name ref="#fern">fern</name> and <name ref="#furze">furze</name> and low <name ref="#broom">broom</name>, crowned with luxuriant hedgerows, and famous for their summer smell of <name ref="#thyme">thyme</name>. How lovely these banks are now—the tall weeds and the <name ref="#gorse">gorse</name> fixed and stiffened in the hoar frost, which fringes round the bright prickly <name ref="#holly">holly</name>, the pendant foliage of the <name ref="#bramble">bramble</name>, and the deep orange leaves of the <name ref="#oak">pollard oaks</name>! Oh, this is rime in its loveliest form! And there is still a berry here and there on the <name ref="#holly">holly</name>, <quote>blushing in its natural coral</quote><!--scw: I have not yet been able to identify this quote--> through the delicate tracery, still a stray hip or haw for the birds, who abound here always. The poor<pb n="33"/> birds, how tame they are, how sadly tame! There is the beautiful and rare crested <name ref="#wren_crested">wren</name>, <quote corresp="#Nat_Hist_Selborne">that shadow of a bird,</quote> <note resp="#ad">Letter XLI to <persName ref="#Pennant_Thomas">Thomas Pennant</persName>in <title>The Natural History of Selborne</title> (Harmondsworth: Penguin Books Ltd, 1987), p. 97.</note> as <persName  ref="#WhiteGilbert">White</persName> of <placeName ref="#Selborne">Selborn</placeName> calls it, perched in the middle of the hedge, nestling as it were amongst the cold bare boughs, seeking, poor pretty thing, for the warmth it will not find. And there, farther on, just under the bank, by the slender runlet, which still trickles between its transparent fantastic margin of thin ice, as if it were a thing of life,—there, with a swift scudding motion, flits, in short low flights, the gorgeous <name ref="#kingfisher">kingfisher</name>, its magnificent plumage of scarlet and blue flashing in the sun, like the glories of some tropical bird. He is come for water to this little spring by the hill side,—water which even his long bill and slender head can hardly reach, so nearly do the fantastic forms of those garland-like icy margins meet over the tiny stream beneath. It is rarely that one sees the shy beauty so close or so long; and it is pleasant to see him in the grace and beauty of his natural liberty, the only way to look at a bird. We used, before we lived in a street, to fix a little board outside the parlour-window, and cover it with bread-crumbs in the hard weather. It was quite delightful to see the pretty things come and feed, to conquer their shyness, and do away their mistrust. First came the more social tribes, <name ref="#robin #wren"><quote>the robin red-breast and the wren,</quote></name><note resp="#scw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> may be quoting from a popular song, several of which contained this phrase. The popular belief that robins were <soCalled>sociable</soCalled> birds was reiterated by <persName ref="#Walton_I">Isaac Walton</persName> in his <title level="m" ref="#Compl_Angler">The Complete Angler</title>.</note><!--scw: unable to identify this quote with certainty, but it’s possible MRM is quoting from a folksong, as there were several old folksongs containing this line. For example: “The robin redbreast and the wren / Coost out about the supper pan; / And or the robin gat a spune / Kitty had the supper dune.” (p.558) Quoted in Edward Newman, The Zoologist: A Popular Miscellany of Natural History. London: John Vander Voorst, 1849:558. Google Books. The source quotes other songs containing this line as well. --> cautiously, suspiciously, picking up a crumb on the wing, with the little keen bright<pb n="34"/> eye fixed on the window; then they would stop for two pecks; then stay till they were satisfied. The shyer birds, tamed by their example, came next; and at last one saucy fellow of a <name ref="#blackbird">blackbird</name>—a sad glutton, he would clear the board in two minutes,—used to tap his yellow bill against the window for more. How <orgName ref="#OVNarratorsFamily">we</orgName> loved the fearless confidence of that fine, frank-hearted creature! And surely he loved us. I wonder the practice is not more general.<note resp="#scw">In her journal, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> describes how she fed small birds at the window.</note>—<said who="#OVNarrator" direct="true"><persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>! <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>! naughty <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>!</said> She has frightened away the <name ref="#kingfisher">kingfisher</name>; and now, in her coaxing penitence, she is covering me with snow. <said who="#OVNarrator" direct="true">Come, <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">pretty May</persName>! it is time to go home.</said></p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <!--<listPerson type="fict" subtype="int">
                    <person xml:id="JackRapley"></person><!-\-scw: cross-ref with 2 Jack Rapley entries from Needham-\->
                    <person xml:id="Frost_Bitten_Gent"></person>
                    <person xml:id="ShiveringLady"></person><!-\-scw: all of these entered into fictionalpeople_OVcorrections on June 22, 2016 but others below not entered-\->
                    <person xml:id="Lieutenant"></person>
                    
                    
                </listPerson>-->
                
                <!--<listPerson type="hist" subtype="ext">
                    <person xml:id="Pennant_Thomas"></person>
                    <person xml:id="WhiteGilbert"></person>
                </listPerson>

                <listPlace>
                    
                </listPlace>
                <listOrg type="person" subtype="fict">
                    <org xml:id="urchins"/>
                    <org xml:id="walkers"/>
                    <org xml:id="riders"/>
                    <org xml:id="LieutenantsChildren"/>
                    <org xml:id="skating_spectators"/>
                    
                </listOrg>
                <listBibl></listBibl>
                <listNym></listNym>-->
            </div>
            
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
